Register of the Poland. Poselstwo (Portugal) Records
Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Poselstwo (Portugal) records,
1919-1957
65010
Poland. Poselstwo (Portugal)
43 manuscript boxes (17.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, and reports, relating to foreign relations between Poland and Portugal between the two world wars, and to foreign relations between Portugal and the Polish Government-in-Exile in London during and after World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1965.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (48 reels).
Historical Note
Polish legation in Portugal and consulate in Lisbon.
Scope and Content Note
The Polish legation in Lisbon was established three years after Poland regained its independence in 1918. It played a rather marginal role in the Polish diplomatic network until the outbreak of the Spanish Civil War, when it supplied Warsaw with vital news on political developments on the Iberian Peninsula, which was especially important because of the participation of a large contingent of Communist Poles.
After September 1939, Portugal no longer recognized General Sikorski's government in London, but the legation was able to survive thanks to the support of General Salazar, and its operations continued uninterrupted. Throughout the war, the legation contributed to the humanitarian efforts in favor of refugees under the direction of Stanislaw Schimitzek, Delegate of the Ministry of Social Welfare.
Like other neutral countries during World War II, Portugal became a center of political maneuvering and exchange of information between the various parties involved in the conflict. Poles were very active as well, particularly in their efforts to establish an alternative alliance in Central Europe, which would counterbalance the Western Powers. This is an aspect of Poland's foreign policy that remains largely unknown, into which this collection gives a good insight.
From Lisbon, Poles also directed their espionage and subversive activities against Germany. The head of the so-called Akcja Kontynentalna was Colonel Jan Kowalewski, whose political agenda remained in conflict with London's official line. Some interesting examples of his initiatives can be found among these records.
However, most of the documents relating to intelligence were destroyed after the war, not only to keep them from the communists but also from former allies, mainly the British. The full story of what they may have contained has to be reconstructed from other sources. One also gets the impression that sensitive documents on the failed post-war plans were removed from the records as well.
The most significant figure in the legation's history was Karol Dubicz-Penther (1937-1944). Among his closest associates was Jozef Potocki, one of the most highly regarded Polish diplomats. Dubicz-Penther was succeeded by Gustaw Potworowski, who remained in his post until 1951, at which point the legation was handed over to Jan Tomaszewski. It operated until the death of the last Honorary Consul, Martin Leslie, in 1977.
The collection was received by the Hoover Institution in 1965, so those last years aren't covered here and the fate of those records is not known.
The records were filed according to the system established by the Ministry of Foreign Affairs before World War II. For the full list of that classification system, please see the register to the Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych collection, also at the Hoover Institution Archives.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; Lisbon (Portugal); Poland.; Poland--Foreign relations--Portugal.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; Portugal.; Portugal--Foreign relations--Poland.
Other Index Terms Related to this Collection
Poland. Konsulat (Lisbon, Portugal)
Series Description
- Series 1-886 (with many gaps) (Box 1-42)
  of bulletins, circulars, communiqués, correspondence, printed matter, questionnaires, receipts, reports, telegrams, arranged numerically
- Photographs, 1931-1939. (Box 43)
  Seventy-two prints depicting various personalities and events
- Scores, n.d. (Box 43)
  Scores entitled "Partytura Pierwszej Brygady. Partitura de Banda. Partitura de Grande Orquestra," sent from Warsaw before Marshal Jozef Pilsudski's trip to Portugal
- Annex. (Box 43)
  Samples of original folders
Container List
- SERIES NO. 1. FOREIGN RELATIONS OF VARIOUS COUNTRIES, NOT INVOLVING POLAND (Box 1)
  - 1934 - Portugal-Germany (Folder 1: 1)
  - 1934-1936 - Portugal-League of Nations (Folder 1: 2)
  - 1935 - Portugal-Great Britain (Folder 1: 3)
  - 1935-1938 - Portugal-Spain (Folder 1: 4)
  - 1936
    - France-Spain (Folder 1: 5)
    - Portugal-Spain (Folder 1: 6)
  - 1936-1938 - Spain-Soviet Union (Folder 1: 7)
  - 1937
    - Portugal
      - Czechoslovakia (Folder 1: 8)
      - France (Folder 1: 9)
    - Spain
      - Germany (Folder 1: 10)
      - Italy (Folder 1: 11)
      - Soviet Union. (Folder 1: 12)
        Includes reports on the Spanish Civil War by the intelligence unit of Oddzial II
- SERIES NO. 3. POLITICAL REPORTS
  - 1934 (Folder 1: 13)
  - 1935 (Folder 1: 14)
  - 1936 (Folder 1: 15)
  - 1937 (Folder 1: 16)
  - 1938
    - General (Folder 1: 17)
    - British diplomatic sources on the Spanish Civil. (Folder 1: 18)
      Reports
    - War Intelligence unit of Oddzial II. (Folder 1: 19)
  - 1939 (Folder 1: 20)
  - 1940 (Folder 1: 21)
  - 1941 (Folder 1: 22)
  - 1942 (Folder 1: 23)
  - 1943 (Folder 1: 24)
  - 1944 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - 1945 (Folder 2: 2)
- SERIES NO. 7. POLITICAL SYSTEM, GOVERNMENT, PARLIAMENT
  - 1922 (Folder 2: 3)
  - 1923 (Folder 2: 4)
  - 1925 (Folder 2: 5)
  - 1926 (Folder 2: 6)
  - 1927 (Folder 2: 7)
  - 1928 (Folder 2: 8)
  - 1929 (Folder 2: 9)
  - 1930 (Folder 2: 10)
  - 1931 (Folder 2: 11)
  - 1932 (Folder 2: 12)
  - 1933 (Folder 2: 13)
  - 1934-1935 (Folder 2: 14)
  - 1936-1937 (Folder 2: 15)
  - 1938
    - General (Folder 2: 16)
    - Soviet Union (Folder 2: 17)
    - Spain (Folder 2: 18)
- SERIES NO. 9. ORGANIZATIONS AND POLITICAL ASSOCIATIONS, 1931 (Folder 2: 19)
- SERIES NO. 11. NATIONALIST AND SEPARATIST MOVEMENTS, 1936 (Folder 2: 20)
- SERIES NO. 12. COMMUNIST MOVEMENTS
  - 1935-1937 (Folder 2: 21)
  - 1937 (Folder 2: 22)
- SERIES NO. 13. MINORITIES OUTSIDE POLAND'S BORDERS, 1938 (Folder 2: 23)
- SERIES NO. 14. COLONIAL POLICY (Box 3)
  - 1924 (Folder 3: 1)
  - 1927 (Folder 3: 2)
  - 1929 (Folder 3: 3)
  - 1930 (Folder 3: 4)
  - 1931 (Folder 3: 5)
  - 1932 (Folder 3: 6)
  - 1933 (Folder 3: 7)
  - 1934 (Folder 3: 8)
  - 1935 (Folder 3: 9)
  - 1935-1937 (Folder 3: 10)
  - 1937 (Folder 3: 11)
  - 1938 (Folder 3: 12)
  - 1939 (Folder 3: 13)
- SERIES NO. 17. PANSLAVISM, 1939-1940 (Folder 3: 14)
- SERIES NO. 19. ECONOMIC RELATIONS OF VARIOUS COUNTRIES, NOT INVOLVING POLAND
  - 1933 (Folder 3: 15)
  - 1934 (Folder 3: 16)
  - 1935 (Folder 3: 17)
  - 1938 (Folder 3: 18)
  - 1939 (Folder 3: 19)
- SERIES NO. 20. ECONOMIC AFFAIRS OF COLONIES, PROTECTORATES, MANDATE COUNTRIES
  - 1937 (Folder 3: 20)
  - 1938 (Folder 3: 21)
- SERIES NO. 21. FINANCES AND CREDITS
  - 1937 (Folder 3: 22)
  - 1938 (Folder 3: 23)
  - 1939 (Folder 3: 24)
  - 1940 (Folder 3: 25)
- SERIES NO. 21a. FINANCES AND CREDITS - GENERAL CONDITIONS, 1936 (Folder 3: 26)
- SERIES NO. 22. INDUSTRY
  - 1936 (Folder 3: 27)
  - 1938 (Folder 3: 28)
- SERIES NO. 23. AGRICULTURE, 1935 (Folder 3: 29)
- SERIES NO. 24. MINING
  - 1933 (Folder 3: 30)
  - 1939 (Folder 3: 31)
- SERIES NO. 28. TRADE (Box 4)
  - 1939 (Folder 4: 1)
  - 1940 (Folder 4: 2)
- SERIES NO. 28b. TRADE, DOMESTIC
  - 1933-1934 (Folder 4: 3)
  - 1935 (Folder 4: 4)
- SERIES NO. 33c. POPULATION - EMIGRATION, 1935 (Folder 4: 5)
- SERIES NO. 39. ECONOMIC REPORTS
  - 1922-1932 (Folder 4: 6)
  - 1934 (Folder 4: 7)
  - 1936. (Folder 4: 8)
    Reports by Tadeusz Romer
  - 1936-1937 (Folder 4: 9)
  - 1937 (Folder 4: 10)
  - 1940 (Folder 4: 11)
  - 1943 (Folder 4: 12)
- SERIES NO. 48. INSTRUCTIONS OF MINISTRY, 1939 (Folder 4: 13)
- SERIES NO. 49. POLITICAL RELATIONS WITH POLAND IN GENERAL
  - 1933
    - Latvia - War predictions (Folder 4: 14)
    - Portugal (Folder 4: 15)
  - 1934 - Portugal (Folder 4: 16)
  - 1936 - Germany (Folder 4: 17)
  - 1937 - Portugal (Folder 4: 18)
  - 1938 - Lithuania (Folder 4: 19)
  - 1939
    - Germany
      - General (Folder 4: 20)
      - Memoranda (Folder 4: 21)
    - Portugal (Folder 4: 22)
    - Soviet Union (Folder 4: 23)
  - 1940
    - Czechoslovakia (Folder 4: 24)
    - France (Folder 4: 25)
    - Germany (Folder 4: 26)
    - Lithuania (Folder 4: 27)
    - Soviet Union (Folder 4: 28)
  - 1941
    - Balkans (Folder 4: 29)
    - Catholic Church - Repression toward the Church (Folder 4: 30)
    - Czechoslovakia (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - France (Folder 5: 2)
    - Germany (Folder 5: 3)
    - Lithuania (Folder 5: 4)
    - Portugal (Folder 5: 5)
    - Romania (Folder 5: 6)
    - Soviet Union
      - General (Folder 5: 7)
      - Deportations (Folder 5: 8)
  - 1942
    - Hungary (Folder 5: 9)
    - Portugal (Folder 5: 10)
    - Soviet Union (Folder 5: 11)
  - 1943
    - Germany - Opole Silesia (Folder 5: 12)
    - Italy (Folder 5: 13)
    - Lithuania (Folder 5: 14)
    - Soviet Union
      - General (Folder 5: 15)
      - Instructions (Folder 5: 16)
  - 1944
    - General (Folder 5: 17)
    - Portugal (Folder 5: 18)
  - 1945 - Portugal (Folder 5: 19)
- SERIES NO. 50. PROPAGANDA IN SPECIFIC POLITICAL ISSUES
  - 1935 - Polish-Czechoslovak relations (Folder 5: 20)
  - 1943 (Folder 5: 21)
  - 1945 (Folder 5: 22)
  - 1945-1947 (Folder 5: 23)
  - 1946 (Folder 5: 24)
  - 1947 (Folder 5: 25)
  - 1948 (Folder 5: 26)
  - 1949 (Folder 5: 27)
- SERIES NO. 51. GRIEVANCES AND COMPENSATIONS SETTLED THROUGH DIPLOMATIC CHANNELS - Germany - Reparations, 1945 (Folder 5: 28)
- SERIES NO. 52. POLITICAL REPORTS. (Box 6)
  Includes reports on talks with Central European satellite countries
  - General
    - 1941 - Romania's position in the war as presented by the King Carol and Pungal (Folder 6: 1)
    - 1943 (Folder 6: 2)
    - 1944 (Folder 6: 3)
    - 1945 (Folder 6: 4)
    - 1947 (Folder 6: 5)
  - Biuletyny Poufne
    - 1943 (Folder 6: 6)
    - 1944 (Folder 6: 7)
    - 1945 (Folder 6: 8)
    - 1946 (Folder 6: 9)
    - 1947 (Folder 6: 10)
    - 1948 (Folder 6: 11)
    - 1949 (Folder 6: 12)
  - Lady Judith Listowel Bulletin, 1945 (Folder 6: 13)
- SERIES NO. 53. NAME INDEX (INSTRUCTIONS) - Polish war aims, 1940 (Folder 6: 14)
- SERIES NO. 57a. ECONOMIC RELATIONS WITH POLAND IN GENERAL
  - 1921 (Folder 6: 15)
  - 1922 (Folder 6: 16)
  - 1925-1927 (Folder 6: 17)
  - 1930 (Folder 6: 18)
  - 1931 (Folder 6: 19)
  - 1932
    - General (Folder 6: 20)
    - Potatoes (Folder 6: 21)
  - 1933 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - 1934 (Folder 7: 2)
  - 1935 (Folder 7: 3)
  - 1937
    - General (Folder 7: 4)
    - Exports (Folder 7: 5)
    - Spain (Folder 7: 6)
  - 1938 (Folder 7: 7)
- SERIES NO. 57b. TRADE AND CLEARING
  - 1934 (Folder 7: 8)
  - 1937 (Folder 7: 9)
- SERIES NO. 57c. STATISTICS
  - 1934 (Folder 7: 10)
  - 1935 (Folder 7: 11)
  - 1936 (Folder 7: 12)
  - 1937 (Folder 7: 13)
  - 1938 (Folder 7: 14)
  - 1939 (Folder 7: 15)
- SERIES NO. 59. TRADE TURNOVER REGULATIONS
  - 1933 (Folder 7: 16)
  - 1935 (Folder 7: 17)
- SERIES NO. 60. PRODUCT CERTIFICATES, 1939 (Folder 7: 18)
- SERIES NO. 61. POLISH CAPITAL AND POLISH ENTERPRISES ABROAD (Box 8)
  - 1934 (Folder 8: 1)
  - 1935 - Sepewe - Spolka Eksportu Przemyslu Obronnego (Folder 8: 2)
  - 1937
    - General (Folder 8: 3)
    - Polska Wytwornia Papierow Wartosciowych (Folder 8: 4)
  - 1938 - Sepewe (Folder 8: 5)
  - 1939
    - General (Folder 8: 6)
    - Sepewe - Spolka Eksportu Przemyslu Obronnego (Folder 8: 7)
  - 1940 - Sepewe - Spolka Eksportu Przemyslu Obronnego (Folder 8: 8)
- SERIES NO. 65. CUSTOM DUTIES, 1938 (Folder 8: 9)
- SERIES NO. 65a. CUSTOM TARIFFS
  - 1935 (Folder 8: 10)
  - 1938 (Folder 8: 11)
  - 1939 (Folder 8: 12)
- SERIES NO. 65c. CUSTOMS LAW, 1937 (Folder 8: 13)
- SERIES NO. 65e. CUSTOMS DUTY OFFICES, 1935 (Folder 8: 14)
- SERIES NO. 67. VETERINARY AND PHYTOPATHOLOGICAL ISSUES
  - 1935 (Folder 8: 15)
  - 1937 (Folder 8: 16)
  - 1938 (Folder 8: 17)
- SERIES NO. 69b. CHAMBERS OF COMMERCE IN POLAND
  - 1930-1931 (Folder 8: 18)
  - 1932-1933 (Folder 8: 19)
  - 1934 (Folder 8: 20)
  - 1935 (Folder 8: 21)
  - 1937 (Folder 8: 22)
- SERIES NO. 70. PUBLICITY IN ECONOMIC AFFAIRS, 1933-1934 (Folder 8: 23)
- SERIES NO. 73. POLITICAL CONDITIONS IN POLAND (Box 9)
  - 1940
    - General (Folder 9: 1)
    - Arrest of Jagiellonian University professors (Folder 9: 2)
  - 1941 (Folder 9: 3)
  - 1943
    - Germany - Extermination of Jews. Diplomatic note (Folder 9: 4)
    - Soviet Union - Katyn Forest Massacre, 1940 (Folder 9: 5)
- SERIES NO. 73a. GERMAN OCCUPATION ZONE
  - 1939 - Fifth column in Pomorze (Pomerania) (Folder 9: 6)
  - 1943 (Folder 9: 7)
- SERIES NO. 73B. SOVIET OCCUPATION ZONE
  - 1944-1945 (Folder 9: 8)
  - 1947 (Folder 9: 9)
- SERIES NO. 78a. LEGAL ASSISTANCE IN CIVIL LAW - Hague Convention, 1926-1932 (Folder 9: 10)
- SERIES NO. 78c. EXTRADITIONS
  - 1934 (Folder 9: 11)
  - 1935 (Folder 9: 12)
  - 1936 (Folder 9: 13)
  - 1939 (Folder 9: 14)
- SERIES NO. 82. COMMERCIAL AND CUSTOMS AGREEMENTS
  - 1921-1930 - International negotiations (Folder 9: 15)
  - 1931 (Folder 9: 16)
  - 1934
    - General (Folder 9: 17)
    - Spain (Folder 9: 18)
  - 1935
    - General
      - General (Folder 9: 19)
      - Ambassador's reports (Box-folder 10: 1)
      - Statistics (Folder 10: 2)
    - Avenant Inc. (Folder 10: 3)
    - Trade agreements
      - Poland (Folder 10: 4)
      - Portugal with France, Italy, Norway, Soviet Union (Folder 10: 5)
  - 1936
    - General (Folder 10: 6)
    - Avenant Inc. (Folder 10: 7)
  - 1937 (Folder 10: 8)
  - 1938
    - General (Folder 10: 9)
    - Portugal's agreements with other countries (Folder 10: 10)
  - 1939 (Folder 10: 11)
- SERIES NO. 85. INSURANCE AND LABOR AGREEMENTS (EXCLUDING POLAND), 1933-1934 (Folder 10: 12)
- SERIES NO. 92. SANITARY AND VETERINARY AGREEMENTS, 1934 (Folder 10: 13)
- SERIES NO. 115. VATICAN'S FOREIGN RELATIONS, 1941 (Folder 10: 14)
- SERIES NO. 122. VATICAN'S RELATIONS WITH POLAND
  - 1941 (Folder 10: 15)
  - 1943 (Folder 10: 16)
- SERIES NO. 125. LEAGUE OF NATIONS SESSIONS, 1936 (Folder 10: 17)
- SERIES NO. 126. LEAGUE OF NATIONS COUNCIL
  - 1935 (Folder 10: 18)
  - 1936 (Folder 10: 19)
- SERIES NO. 126a. LEAGUE OF NATIONS COUNCIL ELECTIONS, 1933 (Folder 10: 20)
- SERIES NO. 133. ARMAMENTS, 1939 (Folder 10: 21)
- SERIES NO. 138. CONFLICTS BETWEEN LEAGUE OF NATIONS MEMBERS, 1935 (Folder 10: 22)
- SERIES NO. 139. INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC COOPERATION UNDER AUSPICES OF LEAGUE OF NATIONS, 1939 (Folder 10: 23)
- SERIES NO. 158. SLAVE TRADE AND CHILD WELFARE
  - 1934 (Folder 10: 24)
  - 1936 (Box-folder 11: 1)
- SERIES NO. 167. INTERNATIONAL TRIBUNALS. ORGANIZATIONAL MATTERS, 1939 April (Folder 11: 2)
- SERIES NO. 171. STANDING MEDIATION COURT IN THE HAGUE, 1940 (Folder 11: 3)
- SERIES NO. 173. DISPUTES BEFORE STANDING MEDIATION COURT IN THE HAGUE - Conflict within Department II, 1938 (Folder 11: 4)
- SERIES NO. 177. INTERNATIONAL LABOUR OFFICE. ORGANIZATION AND PERSONNEL, 1940 (Folder 11: 5)
- SERIES NO. 178. INTERNATIONAL LABOUR OFFICE ACTIVITIES
  - 1934 (Folder 11: 6)
  - 1937 (Folder 11: 7)
- SERIES NO. 183. INTERNATIONAL INSTITUTES AND BUREAUS, 1939 (Folder 11: 8)
- SERIES NO. 184. INTERNATIONAL CONGRESSES, CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS
  - 1925 (Folder 11: 9)
  - 1927 (Folder 11: 10)
  - 1929 (Folder 11: 11)
  - 1930 (Folder 11: 12)
  - 1933
    - General (Folder 11: 13)
    - Land-surveying (Folder 11: 14)
  - 1934
    - General (Folder 11: 15)
    - Geography (Folder 11: 16)
  - 1934-1935 (Folder 11: 17)
  - 1937 (Folder 11: 18)
  - 1938 (Folder 11: 19)
  - 1939 (Folder 11: 20)
- SERIES NO. 190. SCHOLARLY INSTITUTIONS, 1939 (Folder 11: 21)
- SERIES NO. 201. ACADEMIC CELEBRATIONS AND GRANTING OF DIPLOMAS, 1938 (Folder 11: 22)
- SERIES NO. 202. SCIENTIFIC INFORMATION, 1939 (Folder 11: 23)
- SERIES NO. 203. PUBLICATIONS FOR STATE AND SCIENTIFIC INSTITUTIONS AND INDIVIDUALS, 1936 (Folder 11: 24)
- SERIES NO. 203b. POLISH PUBLICATIONS FOR FOREIGNERS, 1940 (Folder 11: 25)
- SERIES NO. 204. MUSEUM, SCIENTIFIC, ARCHIVAL AND LIBRARY COLLECTIONS, 1933-1936 (Folder 11: 26)
- SERIES NO. 211. QUESTIONS RELATED TO GERMAN REPARATIONS
  - 1935 (Folder 11: 27)
  - 1936 (Folder 11: 28)
  - 1940 (Folder 11: 29)
- SERIES NO. 214. MANDATES OF FORMER GERMAN COLONIES, 1937 (Folder 11: 30)
- SERIES NO. 239. INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS
  - 1935 (Folder 11: 31)
  - 1936 (Folder 11: 32)
- SERIES NO. 245. WAR OF 1939 AND POSTWAR PLANNING
  - 1942 (Folder 11: 33)
  - 1943
    - General (Folder 11: 34)
    - Germany (Folder 11: 35)
    - Soviet Union (Folder 11: 36)
- SERIES NO. 263. MINORITIES IN OTHER COUNTRIES, 1935 (Folder 11: 37)
- SERIES NO. 265. TREATIES ON MINORITIES, 1934 (Folder 11: 38)
- SERIES NO. 268. CAUSASUS, 1940 (Folder 11: 39)
- SERIES NO. 273. EMIGRATION POLICY
  - 1934 (Folder 11: 40)
  - 1939 (Folder 11: 41)
  - 1940 (Folder 11: 42)
- SERIES NO. 275. COLONIAL AFFAIRS
  - 1934 (Folder 11: 43)
  - 1937 (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - 1938
    - General (Folder 12: 2)
    - Compagnie de Cabinda (Folder 12: 3)
  - 1939 (Folder 12: 4)
- SERIES NO. 276. CULTURAL AFFAIRS OF EMIGRES, 1935-1936 (Folder 12: 5)
- SERIES NO. 277. POLISH YOUTH STUDYING ABROAD, 1934 (Folder 12: 6)
- SERIES NO. 282. CENTRAL ORGANIZATION OF POLES ABROAD
  - 1934 (Folder 12: 7)
  - 1936-1937 (Folder 12: 8)
- SERIES NO. 287. EMIGRATION OF ETHNIC MINORITIES
  - 1937 - Jews in Angola (Folder 12: 9)
  - 1938. (Folder 12: 10)
    Circulars
  - 1938-1939 (Folder 12: 11)
- SERIES NO. 288. TRANSPORTATION OF EMIGRANTS, 1936 (Folder 12: 12)
- SERIES NO. 292. MINES IN MOZAMBIQUE, 1938 (Folder 12: 13)
- SERIES NO. 297. CENTERS OF POLISH SETTLEMENTS ABROAD
  - 1935-1937 (Folder 12: 14)
  - 1939 - Germans in Poland and Poles in Germany (Folder 12: 15)
  - 1943-1944 - Zwiazek Obywateli Polskich w Lisbonie. (Folder 12: 16)
    Includes references to Vittel
- SERIES NO. 298. POLISH SCHOOOL SYSTEMS ABROAD, 1940 (Folder 12: 17)
- SERIES NO. 299. POLISH EDUCATIONAL, CULTURAL, WELFARE ORGANIZATIONS ABROAD, 1938 (Folder 12: 18)
- SERIES NO. 301. SCOUTING, 1938 (Folder 12: 19)
- SERIES NO. 302. POLITICAL GROUPS ABROAD
  - 1938 (Folder 12: 20)
  - 1940. (Folder 12: 21)
    Includes list of Jews in Poland recommended for possible evacuation(?) by American Jewish organizations
- SERIES NO. 303. POLISH PRESS ABROAD, 1935 (Folder 12: 22)
- SERIES NO. 307. SOCIAL WELFARE FOR EMIGRANTS (Box 13)
  - 1936-1938 (Folder 13: 1)
  - 1939-1940 (Folder 13: 2)
  - 1945 (Folder 13: 3)
- SERIES NO. 308. WORK SEARCH AGENCIES FOR EMIGRANTS
  - 1933 (Folder 13: 4)
  - 1939 - Polish engineers (Folder 13: 5)
  - 1940 (Folder 13: 6)
- SERIES NO. 310. ORGANIZATION OF EMIGRE MOVEMENTS, 1940 (Folder 13: 7)
- SERIES NO. 312. WAR REFUGEES
  - 1940.
    Correspondence
    - Incoming
      - June-August (Folder 13: 8)
      - October (Folder 13: 9)
      - November-December (Folder 13: 10)
    - Outgoing - June-July (Folder 13: 11)
  - 1941 - Romania (Folder 13: 12)
- SERIES NO. 317. ORGANIZATION OF PRESS SERVICES. PLANS AND INSTRUCTIONS
  - 1942 (Folder 13: 13)
  - 1943 (Folder 13: 14)
- SERIES NO. 323. PRESS AND PROPAGANDA REPORTS
  - 1933 (Folder 13: 15)
  - 1938 (Folder 13: 16)
  - 1940-1941 (Folder 13: 17)
  - 1943 (Folder 13: 18)
- SERIES NO. 323a. PRESS REPORTS
  - 1935 (Folder 13: 19)
  - 1936 (Folder 13: 20)
- SERIES NO. 324. PRESS AGENCIES
  - 1934 (Folder 13: 21)
  - 1935-1936 (Folder 13: 22)
- SERIES NO. 324a. POLISH PRESS AGENCIES
  - 1936 (Folder 13: 23)
  - 1939 (Folder 13: 24)
  - 1940 (Folder 13: 25)
- SERIES NO. 325a. POLISH JOURNALS, 1939 (Folder 13: 26)
- SERIES NO. 327b. FOREIGN JOURNALS, 1938-1940 (Folder 13: 27)
- SERIES NO. 328. FACILITIES FOR JOURNALISTS, 1924-1939 (Folder 13: 28)
- SERIES NO. 330. COMMUNIQUES, TELEGRAMS, ARTICLES, BULLETINS FOR PRESS, 1943 (Folder 13: 29)
- SERIES NO. 330a. COMMUNIQUES, TELEGRAMS, ARTICLES, BULLETINS FOR POLISH PRESS
  - 1935 (Folder 13: 30)
  - 1937 (Folder 13: 31)
  - 1938 (Box-folder 14: 1)
  - 1940 (Folder 14: 2)
- SERIES NO. 330b. COMMUNIQUES, TELEGRAMS, ARTICLES, BULLETINS FOR FOREIGN PRESS
  - 1927 (Folder 14: 3)
  - 1928 (Folder 14: 4)
  - 1929 (Folder 14: 5)
- SERIES NO. 330b. COMMUNIQUES, TELEGRAMS, ARTICLES, BULLETINS FOR FOREIGN PRESS
  - 1931 (Folder 14: 6)
  - 1932 (Folder 14: 7)
  - 1933-1934 (Folder 14: 8)
  - 1935 (Folder 14: 9)
  - 1937 (Folder 14: 10)
  - 1938
    - General (Folder 14: 11)
    - Ruthenia (Folder 14: 12)
    - Smigly-Rydz, Edward (Folder 14: 13)
  - 1939
    - General (Folder 14: 14)
    - Poland's military power (Folder 14: 15)
  - 1940
    - General
      - General (Folder 14: 16)
      - Bulletins
        - Boletin de Informacoes da Agencia Transcontinental Press (Folder 14: 17)
        - Servico Polonez de Informacoes (Folder 14: 18)
    - Poland's cultural losses (Folder 14: 19)
  - 1941 (Folder 14: 20)
  - 1942 - Boletin de Informacoes da Agencia Transcontinental Press (Folder 14: 21)
- SERIES NO. 332. PUBLICITY IN LITERATURE, ARTS, MUSIC, THEATER, OPERA, BALLET, NATIONAL COSTUMES (Box 15)
  - 1935 (Folder 15: 1)
  - 1936 (Folder 15: 2)
  - 1938 (Folder 15: 3)
  - 1939 (Folder 15: 4)
  - 1940-1941 (Folder 15: 5)
- SERIES NO. 333. PUBLICITY IN FILM, SLIDES, AND PHOTOGRAPHY
  - 1933 (Folder 15: 6)
  - 1934 (Folder 15: 7)
  - 1935 (Folder 15: 8)
  - 1936
    - General (Folder 15: 9)
    - List of journalists (Folder 15: 10)
  - 1938 (Folder 15: 11)
  - 1939 (Folder 15: 12)
- SERIES NO. 334. PUBLICITY IN RADIO
  - 1930 (Folder 15: 13)
  - 1935 (Folder 15: 14)
- SERIES NO. 335. PUBLICITY IN SPORT
  - 1928-1930 - Equestrian competitions (Folder 15: 15)
  - 1938 (Folder 15: 16)
  - 1939 (Folder 15: 17)
- SERIES NO. 336. LECTURES, 1930-1933 (Folder 15: 18)
- SERIES NO. 337. CELEBRATIONS AND COMMEMORATIONS, 1938 (Folder 15: 19)
- SERIES NO. 337b. PILSUDSKI, JOZEF - Madeira, 1934 (Folder 15: 20)
- SERIES NO. 338. FAIRS
  - 1930-1935 (Folder 15: 21)
  - 1936
    - Targi Poznanskie (Folder 15: 22)
    - Targi Wschodnie (Folder 15: 23)
  - 1938
    - Targi Poznanskie (Folder 15: 24)
    - Targi Wschodnie (Folder 15: 25)
  - 1939
    - Targi Poznanskie (Folder 15: 26)
    - Targi Wschodnie (Folder 15: 27)
- SERIES NO. 340. EXHIBITIONS - Photography, 1936 (Folder 15: 28)
- SERIES NO. 340a. ARTISTIC EXHIBITIONS, 1936
  - General
    - General (Folder 15: 29)
    - Catalogs (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - Lukomski, Jerzy (Folder 16: 2)
  - Woodcuts (Folder 16: 3)
- SERIES NO. 340b. MUSEUM EXHIBITIONS, 1938 (Folder 16: 4)
- SERIES NO. 340d. ECONOMIC EXHIBITIONS
  - 1934 (Folder 16: 5)
  - 1936 (Folder 16: 6)
- SERIES NO. 341. PUBLICATIONS
  - 1933 (Folder 16: 7)
  - 1939 (Folder 16: 8)
- SERIES NO. 341a. POLITICAL PUBLICATIONS